All right.
Hey, I will get started then. Okay.
So thank you so much everyone.
My name is Jesse Ward.
I am a digital archivist by trade.
I'm based in Toronto, Canada,
and I'm an independent artist
working in experimental interactive
nonfiction.
So today, I want to show you
a work of electronic literature
that I've built on the premise
that every photograph is an atom
in a massive structure of narrative
hypertext that we can navigate,
because when any two people
are photographed in the same place
at the same moment,
they are connected in a narrative
of all visually recorded human activity,
and we can explore that narrative
to understand more about the story
we all share that has been recorded
through photography.
So we're looking at a family photo
right now.
This is a picture of me
with my mom in 1994,
and I want to start here
starting somewhere small,
because this is something
we're all familiar with.
If you're lucky, you have family
photo albums at home.
You'll see photos like this of yourself
as a child with your parents,
and you have memories
of what was happening.
If you keep going through the albums
and you find older photos, you'll see
photos of your parents with their parents
and you can start to infer
what's happening
based on stories you've heard.
But here's where it gets interesting
you'll eventually reach older
photos of your grandparents
with people who you can't recognize.
You'll see photos that nobody alive
maybe can tell you who is in those photos,
but you know that those photos
are still part of your family narrative.
So you start reading the photographs
themselves.
Who keeps appearing in these pictures?
What are they wearing?
Where do they keep standing?
What you're what you're doing is you start
constructing narrative from adjacency,
because adjacency is what you have to go
by when you're unraveling that mystery.
So this experience of reading
unlabeled proximity in photos
as a story is something that
almost everyone has experienced
with a photo that you've come across.
The project that I want to share with you
is an attempt to do this at the scale
of the entire photographic era,
and I'll explore what I found with you.
So the next slide here,
we were just looking at me
with my mom in 1994.
Now this is a picture of me
with the entertainer, 50 Cent, last year
in Toronto, promoting his Branson cognac
at a promotional event.
And now, think about what
sits between those two photos.
It's kind of funny, but there's everyone
that I've ever been photographed with.
Everyone my mom has ever been
photographed with, everyone 50 Cent
has ever been photographed with.
If you go two degrees out,
you start reaching basically everyone.
And this is the popular theory.
It's been documented and the Milgram
experiments of six degrees of separation.
But when we look at this through photos,
we start to realize that every photograph
in the world tagged with the people in
it is a structure
that already exists intangibly.
And my project, a network of time,
is my ongoing effort to excavate
this international graph of all group
photos ever taken to make it tangible.
The claim that I want to make today
is that a photograph in this system is
is not just an illustration,
but every photo of multiple people
is a narrative atom in this story.
It's the smallest unit of nonfiction
that can carry story, and it's in a photo.
And one photo on its own already
does this.
Now we're looking at 50 Cent with Kobe
Bryant and Meryl Streep.
And when you see a photo like this,
you already start to ask questions.
You might start wondering,
how close are they standing?
Are they good friends? Have they known
each other for a long time?
How casual is the background?
What's happening?
What on earth
was this event that they were at?
Because when we aren't given an explicit
narrative, we start to build one.
And that's the engine that this work
runs on.
The real meaning arrives
when these atoms actually start to change,
like we've just seen in these three photos
and generate narratives.
So I want to show
you this project live, in
a live demo here.
So the work is hosted on the website
network of Time.com.
And I'm going to share my screen again
on a different window.
So what we're looking at right
now is an interactive,
infinite slideshow of all of the photos
that I've collected for this project.
The database currently holds
almost 30,000 verified people
across more than 28,000 photographs
and screenshots that I have discovered
and annotated on and off.
As I've tended to this project
over the last seven years,
spanning the whole photographic
era we're seeing right now.
Figures
from mid-century politics, Henry Wallace
and the Norwegian politician Trygve Lie.
There he is with David Rockefeller.
And this will go on and on through people
connected through photos.
So notice what each step here represents.
It's not a link in a menu,
but each photo is a self-contained
fragment of nonfiction.
Now we see Rockefeller
with Castro and Castro with a journalist.
Each photo is a self-contained
fragment of nonfiction.
There was a real day,
a real room, a reason that two people
stood in the frame together
even if they didn't interact.
The path doesn't explain itself,
but the story is
whatever accumulates
as we move through the slideshow.
So you can click on any photo
to actually reveal more information,
because it's important that this is
documented, sources are covered,
and every person that can be
identified has been tagged
and annotated
so you could explore more information,
see what other photos they are in,
and navigate the entire graph this way.
But every sequence of photos
when you just watch
this slideshow produces
its own story on demand.
So photographs haven't
actually been around for a very long time.
The spine of this graph starts with
the British royal family in the 1850s,
because the first group photographs
are basically Queen Victoria
and her family,
and then Queen Elizabeth alone
connects most of the 20th century.
Now, there's a feature in this platform
that can help produce context or produce
serendipity
for the connections between any two people
by tracing connections.
If we want to take a look at how brief
the scope of the history of photography
is, we can take a look at someone
like a very popular contemporary streamer.
And this is an experiment that I know
some teachers that I'm friends with
have done in their classrooms, is to show
contemporary people to historic figures.
With this website, let's choose
the popular streamer IShowSpeed and Queen
Victoria's mom, Princess
Victoria of Saxe-Coburg Saalfeld,
and let's see how they can be
matched through history.
So it runs the shortest path algorithm
and we see that IShowSpeed met
the footballer
David Beckham last year in Germany.
The next picture is
Beckham meeting Queen Elizabeth ten
years ago in Buckingham Palace.
Now this is a photo of her christening.
We see her highlighted here
as a baby in May 1926,
and in the background
we see Prince Arthur.
And then this photo is from
1854,
Prince Arthur with Princess Victoria.
So he's here as a child.
She's here in the background.
So the 1850s are
when we see the first group photos
in the historic record,
and we see right here
that we can get there in
just about four photos from anyone today.
However,
when we perform a shortest path match
like this,
the narrative is going to be biased.
The most densely connected
people in the graph.
Whenever you pick two random people
and see how they're connected,
you'll generally always travel through
either a world leader,
a royal family member, or a talk show host
because these people
in the photographic records
serve as mega hubs, hyper connectors
like particle colliders
across all kinds of different people.
We see Queen Elizabeth met
hundreds of world leaders in her life.
She also met Charlie Chaplin,
who met Albert Einstein.
And just about anyone in the world
is within five degrees of these people.
We see if we try and match random people
through the photos.
So when we're just watching this,
I mean, we've seen a huge a huge change.
We've gone from the mid century politics
to now we're looking at tech leaders
and tech interviewers, but if we refresh
the page, it would be a new set.
And we might see some
economists in Bangladesh,
or we might see musicians in Angola.
It behaves almost like a dream,
because you can get to anyone
in the world through a tonal whiplash
in just a few photos.
It's unpredictable, tonally whiplash,
but it's never invented.
Every transition we see
is grounded in evidence that we can review
by following the links.
It's strange, but true.
So people read this as a narrative,
and there are four reasons why
there's continuity, where one person
is always carrying the sequence forward.
So there's a protagonist.
Even if the protagonist keeps changing,
there's a transformation
where the context keeps shifting.
We go from formal interviews to candid
photos, paparazzi shots, selfies,
formal events, weddings, professional
documentation, or social media.
There's surprise where you can get
from someone like Frida Kahlo
to professional wrestlers in four photos,
you can never predict where you're going.
We see Barbra
Streisand here with Taylor Swift,
but we could have easily
seen her with Coco Chanel
and then got into Vincent van
Gogh in just a few photos.
And there's a meta narrative
for anyone who discovers the site.
Who made this?
How many people are in here?
Would I find myself in here
who could never appear here?
And that last question haunts me,
because one of the questions that comes up
here is who is chosen to be included?
For example, there are only a few photos
of Harriet Tubman with other people,
and I can't connect any of those
to this graph.
The archive has edges,
and the edges are based on who photography
captured,
who photography excluded, and why,
and then who prioritized being added
to this graph and why.
I built the first version of this site
in 2019 as a coding experiment,
and I thought it was fun
when I had a few hundred photos
and I could connect
Simone de Beauvoir to Tupac, for example.
But seven years later,
working on this on and off,
there's a small community
because the website
does invite submissions where I want to
include as diverse range of content
as possible and people's personal lives.
For example, there is a small community
of contributors.
There's a man in Warsaw named Viktor,
who is personally added more than 300
Polish rappers and streamers to the site,
which is an entire subcultural graph
that I would have never added myself,
probably
with the time that I put into this.
But now about 4000 people a month who view
this site can wander through that.
So my conclusion is
that we can make history function
as an interface,
a form of computational nonfiction
that reveals how deeply and oddly
everyone is connected.
This is something that electronic
literature is uniquely built to do.
It's built
to take evidence of entanglement
and make it readable, make it navigable,
and to dissolve artificial boundaries
between different concepts,
or in this case, to dissolve
artificial boundaries between different
groups of people by proving proximity.
Network of time is my attempt
at making this legible.
It's a nonfiction hypertext
with no true author because it's random
and no ending, but it's written by
everyone who has ever stood
in the frame together, and then everyone
who has contributed to this project.
And it's still being written and will be
something that I continue for a long time.
So we'll see how far the graph
really gets.
That's the presentation
that I had prepared for today.
Thank you so much.